American Academy in Rome
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
- Board of Trustees Records, 1897-1957, undated, Series 2:; (box 1-17; 15.32 linear ft.)
  - Records of Officers, 1897-1957, undated, 2.3:
    - Secretaries, 1898-1947, undated, 2.3.3:
      - C. Grant La Farge (Box 9, Reel 5763)
        - Mead, William R. (President), 1912-1925 (Box 10, Reel 5765)
          (includes letters concerning appointment of director Carter, revision of by-laws, endowment fund, Villa Aurelia, La Farge's ideas on the role of the secretary, Mead Fund to support a fellowship in architecture, women fellows, deaths of Carter and Trowbridge)
        - Mellon, Edward P. (Acting Secretary), undated, 1916-1919 (Box 10, Reel 5765)
        - Members of the Corporation, 1915-1917 (Box 10, Reel 5765)
          (includes list of those who acknowledged receipt of membership certificates, correspondence regarding compiling an accurate list of all major contributors, confusion about titles for donors at various levels)
        - Millet, Frank D., Memorial Service and Endowed Chair of the Fine Arts, 1912 (Box 10, Reel 5765)
        - Morgan, J. Pierpont, Jr. (Trustee), 1913-1916 (Box 10, Reel 5765)
          (correspondence, receipt, agreements regarding loan for Janiculum improvements)
        - Morgan, J. Pierpont, Sr. (Trustee), 1912-1913 (Box 10, Reel 5765)
          (acceptance of Janiculum property adjoining Villa Aurelia, correspondence concerning construction loan)
        - Norton, Charles D. (Trustee), 1913-1923 (Box 10, Reel 5765)
          (about endowment fund, titles for various categories of contributors; also, thank you letters)
        - Pine, John B. (Legal Counsel), 1912-1922 (Box 10, Reel 5765)
          (includes correspondence about publicity, revision of by-laws, estate of Jessie B. Carter)
        - Publications--Memoirs of The American Academy in Rome and Monographs, 1914-1920 (Box 10, Reel 5765)
          (correspondence, reports, recommendations, agreement with Yale University Press)
        - Rockefeller Foundation, 1914 (Box 10, Reel 5765)
          (correspondence concerning grant to academy)
        - Sanders, Henry (Acting Director, School of Classical Studies), 1915 (Box 10, Reel 5765)
          (regarding his appointment,)
        - School of Classical Studies, 1914-1921 (Box 10, Reel 5765)
          (includes historical sketch, letters about fellows, summer school)
        - Secretary of State, 1914 (Box 10, Reel 5765)
          (correspondence regarding the academy in Rome, fellows, probable future war conditions and developments)
        - Stevens, Gorham Phillips (Director, Rome 1919; 1917-1932Director, School of Fine Arts 1913-1917, Acting Director, 1912-1932) (Box 10, Reel 5765-5766)
          (includes correspondence about the death of Millet, appointment of director Carter, Stevens's new title, shipping of student work, exhibitions, Villa Mirafiore, married fellows, Rotch and Lazarus scholarships, finances, expenses, progress of Janiculum improvements, director Carter's death; list of all domestic help in Rome with their salaries, duties, and schedules outlined; problems with bursar, Charles Laurie, war work, Red Cross use of the Main Building as a hospital, Professor Clark's lecture tour for Italian government, summer school)
        - Trowbridge, Breck (Committee on the School of Fine Arts), undated, 1912-1925 (Box 10, Reel 5766)
          (correspondence about endowment fund subscriptions, J. P. Morgan, Sr., exhibitions, gift of Julliard Fellowship)
        - Trustees, undated, 1911-1931 (Box 10, Reel 5766)
          (correspondence with individual trustees, mainly regarding routine administrative matters; also, form letters and letters addressed to the trustees in general; includes problem with bursar, Charles Laurie; provisions for men who entered military service during their fellowship term)
        - United States Trust Company, 1913-1919 (Box 10, Reel 5766)
        - Van Buren, A. W. (Librarian), 1916-1917 (Box 10, Reel 5766)
        - Villa Aurelia, 1912-1915 (Box 10, Reel 5766)
          (includes correspondence about construction progress on the New Building; improvements to Villa Aurelia; purchase of adjoining property with blueprint of Otis elevator stored in OV folder 37; loan agreement with J. P. Morgan, Sr., with Villa Mirafiore as collateral, and agreement for later increase in the amount of the loan; Heyland bequest, taxes)
        - Villa Doccia (Florence, Italy), 1920 (Box 10, Reel 5766)
          (includes copy of Gorham P. Stevens' report to the board with photographs; blueprints of ground and first floor plans stored in OV folder 37)
        - Walters, Henry (Finance Committee), 1912-1932 (Box 10, Reel 5766)
          (includes notice of meeting about Villa Mirafiore with floor plan and site drawings)
        - West, Andrew (Committee on the School of Classical Studies), 1915-1918 (Box 10, Reel 5766)
          (includes correspondence concerning the Advisory Committee, Professors Clark and Curtis)
        - Wilkins, H. Blakiston (Executive Secretary, Rome), 1919-1921 (Box 10, Reel 5766)
          (includes correspondence regarding purchase of adjacent property, need for Wilkins to reside on the premises, shipment of student work, condition of Villa Chiaraviglio, staffing changes)
        - Wolfe, W.R. (Assistant Secretary), undated, 1909-1912 (Box 10, Reel 5766)
          (mainly letters written during Millet's absences, apprising him of academy activities and correspondence received)
      - William B. Dinsmoor, General Correspondence, 1944 (Box 10, Reel 5766)
        (includes letters concerning passport difficulties, thanks to the Minister of Switzerland and the Swiss Legation in Italy for assistance to the Academy during World War II)
      - H. Richardson Pratt (Box 10, Reel 5766)
        - General Correspondence, 1945 (Box 10, Reel 5766)
        - Finance Committee, 1945 (Box 10, Reel 5766)
        - James, Henry (First Vice President; Acting President; resignation), 1945 (Box 10, Reel 5766)
        - Publicity, 1946 (Box 10, Reel 5766)
          (press release announcing appointment of Director Roberts)
        - Roberts, Laurance P. (Director, Rome), 1947 (Box 10, Reel 5766)
          (brief summary of activities)
        - Vatican Payments, 1945 (Box 10, Reel 5766)
          (concerns the academy's loan repayment)
    - Treasurers, 1904-1947, undated, 2.3.4:
      The Treasurers' records are comprehensive only for William A. Boring (3.25 linear feet), who held the position for nearly three decades. The correspondence and records of Arthur H. Crane, assistant treasurer, and Jerome D. Greene, acting treasurer, are interfiled with Boring's records. Records of other treasurers, William R. Mead, Leon Fraser, and Lindsay Bradford, are scant, measuring a folder or two each. Files of treasurer H. Siddons Mowbray can be found with his secretary's files.
      Records are arranged chronologically by treasurer with the names of the treasurer at the top of each file group indicated in bold type. Within the file group for each treasurer, general correspondence files are followed by other files arranged alphabetically by subject or by name of the person to whom the file relates.
      - William R. Mead (Box 11, Reel 5766)
        - General Correspondence, 1905-1910 (Box 11, Reel 5766)
          (includes letters concerning endowment fund)
        - Breck, George W. (Director, Rome), 1904-1905 (Box 11, Reel 5766)
          (includes correspondence about academy finances and expenses, and condition of property)
        - Financial Reports, Rome, 1905/06-1908/09 (Box 11, Reel 5766)
        - Invoices, 1905-1908 (Box 11, Reel 5766)
        - Millet, Frank D. (Secretary), undated, 1904-1910 (Box 11, Reel 5766)
          (includes letters regarding the endowment fund)
        - Rinehart Scholarship, 1905 (Box 11, Reel 5766)
          (includes correspondence with Rinehart scholarship committee chairman concerning expenses and arrangements for shipping Charles Keck's work)
      - William A. Boring (Box 11, Reel 5766)
        - General Correspondence, undated, 1909-1936 (Box 11, Reel 5766)
          (mainly routine administrative matters; also, includes correspondence about periodical subscriptions for library, correspondence with competition finalists and fellowship winners concerning reimbursement for expenses, endowment fund)
        - Letterpress Books, 1914-1918 (Box 11, Reel 5766-5767)
          (copies of outgoing letters, with an alphabetical index for each volume, vol. 1, Oct. 1914-June 1915; vol. 2, April 1916-July 1918)
        - Academy Properties, 1920-1921 (Box 11, Reel 5767)
          (includes chart indicating cost and value of each property, size, present use, and annual upkeep costs; acquisition of adjoining properties, site plan)
        - Aldrich, Chester H. (Director, Rome), 1935-1937 (Box 11, Reel 5767)
          (includes correspondence concerning Italian income tax, details of fellow Harold Bisbee's illness and return to the United States)
        - Audit Reports, 1910/11-1937/38 (Box 11, Reel 5767)
        - Banking, Banca Commerciale Italiana Trust Co., 1931-1933 (Box 11, Reel 5767-5768)
        - Banking, United States Trust Co., 1928-1934 (Box 11, Reel 5767)
        - Breck, George W. (Director, Rome), 1909-1910 (Box 11, Reel 5768)
          (mainly routine administrative matters; includes letter with diagram concerning adjoining property now for sale, construction of new studios)
        - Budget, 1914/15-1937/38 (Box 11, Reel 5768)
        - Carter, Jesse Benedict (Director, American School of Classical Studies, Rome; Director, Rome), 1911-1918 (Box 12, Reel 5768)
          (includes correspondence regarding merger with the American School of Classical Studies in Rome and directorship of the new institution, funds transferred from the American School of Classical Studies in Rome, Janiculum construction; also, death of director Carter and settlement of his academy accounts)
        - College and University Annual Subscriptions, School of Classical Studies, 1914-1924 (Box 12, Reel 5768)
          (includes list of contributing institutions)
        - Crowninshield, Frederic (Director, Rome), 1909-1910 (Box 12, Reel 5768)
          (routine administrative matters; opinions of Villa Aurelia, including letter from Mrs. Crowninshield reporting opinions of Herriman, Burnham and others concerning Villa Aurelia's suitability)
        - Davico, Riccardo (Secretary, Rome), 1921-1937 (Box 12, Reel 5768-5769)
          (financial statements and accounts)
        - Day, Frank Miles (Acting President), 1909-1910 (Box 12, Reel 5769)
          (letters about his resignation, Villa Aurelia)
        - Donor Lists, 1914-1919 (Box 12, Reel 5769)
        - Eli Loan Fund, 1914-1915 (Box 12, Reel 5769)
        - Endowment, 1910-1938 (Box 12, Reel 5769)
          (includes correspondence with donors, discussion of plans for fundraising, subscriptions from trustees, McKim column, lists of donors)
        - Endowment--Boston Committee, 1914-1932 (Box 12, Reel 5769)
        - Endowment--Memorial to Founders, 1909-1928 (Box 12, Reel 5770)
        - Finance Committee, 1924-1936 (Box 12, Reel 5770)
        - Financial Reports, Rome, 1909/10-1913 (Box 12, Reel 5770)
        - Financial Reports, Rome, 1914-1919 (Box 13, Reel 5770)
        - Greene, Jerome D. (Trustee), 1923-1927 (Box 13, Reel 5770)
        - Guernsey, Roscoe (Executive Secretary), 1919-1922; 1931-1933 (Box 13, Reel 5770)
          (includes correspondence about extending fellowship time for particular students, revision of by-laws, contributions to endowment fund, Horatio Parker Fund, staffing, closing buildings to reduce expenses)
        - Hewlett, James Monroe (Director, Rome), 1932-1935 (Box 13, Reel 5770)
          (correspondence regarding students and staff, finances, expenses, housing, academy loans to Hewlett, fellow Olindo Grossi's report of his activities and progress, resignation of fellow Richard Lattimore)
        - Invoices, Miscellaneous, 1911-1920 (Box 13, Reel 5770)
        - Janiculum Land Purchases, 1921-1926 (Box 13, Reel 5770)
          (stored in ov folder 37: copies of legal documents [in Italian], site drawings, and correspondence with donors)
        - Thomas Spencer Jerome Lectureship, 1922-1945 (Box 13, Reel 5770)
        - La Farge, C. Grant (Secretary), 1912-1917 (Box 13, Reel 5770)
        - Lamond, Felix (Professor of Music), 1920-1940 (Box 13, Reel 5770-5771)
          (includes correspondence about donations to the Music Department and the Horatio Parker Fund, purchase of library from the Trinity School of Church Music, activities of students and staff, typical day's schedule, personal finances and plans)
        - Lamond Fund, 1931 (Box 13, Reel 5771)
          (correspondence concerning a fund donated by Mrs. Henry Fairfield Osborn to provide for Professor Lamond's retirement)
        - Landi, Claude P. (Secretary, Rome), 1909-1910 (Box 13, Reel 5771)
        - Laurie, Charles (Secretary, Rome; Manager; Bursar), 1910-1917 (Box 13, Reel 5771)
          (includes accounts of payments to fellows)
        - Library Donations, 1920-1929 (Box 13, Reel 5771)
        - McClellan, George B. (Library Committee), 1920-1927, 1933-1934 (Box 13, Reel 5771)
          (includes reports of visit to Rome analyzing staff responsibilities, facilities, suggestions about Villa Aurelia, detailed discussion of how to improve school administration and students' experience)
        - Mead, William R. (President), 1910-1928 (Box 13, Reel 5771)
          (includes letters about subscriptions to endowment fund, McKim memorial, Villa Aurelia bequest, thoughts on appointment of a new director, trustee nominations, New Building, director Carter's participation in fundraising, Ely Loan Fund, Professors Lamond and Fairbanks, Boston committee, staff appointments and housing, advisability of establishing an Atelier in Rome under the auspices of the academy, housing for women students, observations of fellows, collaborative problem, difficulties with fellow Victor L. S. Hafner, estimated expenses for three years at the academy, discussion of increasing fellowship stipends, death of Trowbridge)
        - Mellon, E. P. (Trustee; Acting Secretary), 1918-1927 (Box 13, Reel 5771)
          (mainly concerning endowment fund)
        - Millet, Frank D. (Secretary) and W. R. Wolfe (Assistant Secretary), n.d, 1909-1912 (Box 13, Reel 5771)
          (includes correspondence about director Crowninshield, students, Villa Aurelia, endowment fund and McKim column contributions, McKim's death, competition expenses, acquisition of additional office space in Chemists' Club)
        - Millet, Frank D., Estate of, 1912-1916 (Box 13, Reel 5771)
          (settlement of accounts with son)
        - Moore, Edward C. (Donor), 1920-1929 (Box 13, Reel 5771)
        - Morgan, J. Pierpont, Jr. (Trustee), 1916-1921 (Box 13, Reel 5771)
          (offer to cancel loan if the academy raises a corresponding amount for a permanent endowment; correspondence concerning endowment fund)
        - Morgan, J. Pierpont, Sr. (Trustee), 1910-1911 (Box 13, Reel 5771)
          (payment of his subscription on the condition that the American Academy in Rome and the American School of Classical Studies in Rome unite)
        - Moses, Lionel (Associate Secretary), 1914-1918 (Box 13, Reel 5771)
        - Ogle, Marbury B. (Professor in Charge of Classical Studies), 1934 (Box 13, Reel 5771)
          (correspondence concerning possible financial irregularities)
        - Osborn, Mrs. H. Fairfield (Donor), 1923-1927 (Box 13, Reel 5771)
          (regarding funding for the Music Department)
        - Parrish, Samuel (Donor), 1924-1931 (Box 13, Reel 5771)
          (regarding funding for a Parrish Art Museum fellowship)
        - Pine, John B. (Trustee; Legal Counsel), undated, 1911-1919 (Box 13, Reel 5771)
          (includes correspondence about amending by-laws to provide for consolidation with the American School of Classical Studies in Rome, use of academy property for Red Cross purposes, payments from sale of Villa Mirafiore)
        - Platt, Charles (President), 1928, 1933 (Box 13, Reel 5771)
          (includes letters regarding advisability of Metropolitan Museum representation on board of trustees, personnel problems in Rome)
        - Pope, John Russell (President), 1934-1935 (Box 13, Reel 5771)
        - Publicity Fund, 1917 (Box 13, Reel 5771)
        - Reports of William A. Boring's Visits to Rome, undated, 1918-1926 (Box 13, Reel 5771)
        - Report of William A. Boring as Visiting Professor of Fine Arts at the American Academy in Rome, 1930 (Box 13, Reel 5771)
        - Richardson, William Symmes (Professor of Fine Arts), 1923-1929 (Box 13, Reel 5771)
          (letter about adjacent lot he now owns, with diagram of the area)
        - Rockefeller Foundation Pledge, 1914-1923 (Box 13, Reel 5771)
          (10 year grant for general operating expenses, pledge to endowment fund)
        - Rowell, Frank B. (Assistant Secretary), 1916-1918 (Box 13, Reel 5771)
        - Stevens, Gorham Phillips (Director, Rome [1912 and 1917-1933]; Director, School of Fine Arts [1913-1917]), 1912-1933 (Box 14, Reel 5771-5772)
          (includes correspondence about Millet's death, extra expenses borne by sculptors, New Building progress, exhibitions, library books requested, settlement of accounts after director Carter's death, staff and student activities, use of Main Building for convalescent hospital, housing, bequest and purchase of library books, Fairbanks' qualifications, repairs to property, staffing for School of Classical Studies, acquisition of additional Janiculum properties, Atelier sponsored by the Academy)
        - Taxes, 1926-1937 (Box 14, Reel 5772)
          (includes copies of city, state, and federal returns, with related correspondence; legal advice concerning Italian income tax)
        - Treasurer's Statements, 1911-1924 (Box 14, Reel 5772)
        - Van Buren, Albert W. (Librarian; Museum Curator; Editor; Professor of Archaeology), 1915-1926, 1935 (Box 14, Reel 5772)
          (mainly concerns routine financial matters; also, correspondence about Century Club membership; reprint of Van Buren's article, "The Technique of Stucco Ceilings at Pompeii" from The Journal of Roman Studies)
        - Villa Aurelia, 1909-1911 (Box 14, Reel 5772)
          (letters about value of the property, Mrs. Heyland's will, opinion of Villa Aurelia's suitability as headquarters of the academy; agreement with J. Pierpont Morgan, Sr., for construction loan, with Villa Mirafiore as collateral; legal advice concerning taxes owed)
        - Villa Mirafiore, 1919-1920 (Box 14, Reel 5772)
          (documents concerning sale of the property, including appraisal)
        - Wilkins, H. Blakiston (Executive Secretary, Rome), 1919-1922 (Box 14, Reel 5772)
          (includes correspondence about housing, retraction of his resignation, rising expenses, clarification of duties, acceptance of resignation)
      - Leon Fraser (Box 14, Reel 5772)
        - General Correspondence, 1939-1945 (Box 14, Reel 5772)
          (includes minutes of Committee in Charge; report of burglary at Villino Bellaci, with list of missing and damaged items)
        - Davico, Riccardo (Secretary, Rome), 1938-1945 (Box 14, Reel 5772)
          (financial reports and related correspondence)
        - Vatican Payments, 1943-1945 (Box 14, Reel 5772)
          (correspondence regarding monthly accounts for academy expenses advanced by the Vatican)
      - Lindsay Bradford (Box 14, Reel 5772)
        - Chase National Bank, 1945-1947 (Box 14, Reel 5772)
        - Morey, C. R. (Director, Rome), 1945-1946 (Box 14, Reel 5772)
          (includes letters concerning reopening of the academy after World War II)
        - Vatican Payments, 1945 (Box 14, Reel 5772)
    - Individual Trustees, 1902-1946, undated, 2.3.5:
      Included here are records of individual trustees (2.75 linear feet) created or maintained by each in his capacity as trustee. These vary in size from one folder to 1.25 linear feet. Trustees represented are: Chester H. Aldrich, John Lambert Cadwalader, Gilmore D. Clarke, James C. Egbert, Barry Faulkner, Allan C. Johnson, William M. Kendall, C. Grant La Farge, Edward P. Mellon, Charles Dyer Norton, Charles A. Platt, John Russell Pope, Edward K. Rand, John c. Rolfe, James Kellum Smith, S. Breck Trowbridge, Ferruccio Vitale, John Quincy Adams Ward, Andrew f. West, and William L. Westerman. Several Trustees also served the Academy as officers or staff, and records regarding those activities will be found in the files relating to those appointments. Brief biographical notes for each trustee included here can be found in Appendix B.
      Records are arranged alphabetically by name of trustee with the names of the trustee at the top of each file group indicated in bold type. Within the file group for each trustee, general correspondence files are followed by other files arranged alphabetically by subject or by name of the person to whom the file relates.
      - Chester H. Aldrich (Box 14, Reel 5772)
        - General Correspondence, 1933-1935 (Box 14, Reel 5772)
          (includes correspondence regarding possible candidates for new position of assistant to the director, fellowship competition, preparations for moving to Rome to assume post of director)
        - Guernsey, Roscoe (Executive Secretary), 1933-1934 (Box 14, Reel 5772)
          (correspondence about collaborative problem, fellowship competition, shipment of student work)
        - Hewlett, James Monroe (Director, Rome), 1933-1935 (Box 14, Reel 5772)
          (Committee on the School of Fine Arts business including exhibitions and evaluation of current fellows)
        - La Farge, C. Grant (Secretary), 1934 (Box 14, Reel 5772)
        - McClellan, George B. (Vice President; Acting President), 1933 (Box 14, Reel 5772)
        - Pope, John Russell (President), 1934-1935 (Box 14, Reel 5772)
          (includes correspondence about Hewlett's personal finances, new fellows, and quality of student work)
      - John Lambert Cadwalader, Correspondence, 1904-1910 (Box 14, Reel 5772)
        (includes items concerning incorporation and fundraising)
      - Gilmore D. Clarke, Correspondence, 1945 (Box 14, Reel 5772)
        (concerns fellowships, opinions about whether to sell Villa Aurelia, finances, expenses)
      - James C. Egbert (Box 14, Reel 5772)
        - AA-AC (Box 14, Reel 5772)
        - Aldrich, Chester (Chairman, Committee on the School of Fine Arts; Director, Rome), 1933-1940 (Box 14, Reel 5772)
          (includes ideas about future direction of academy, newsletter excerpts, staffing)
        - ALL - AR, 1921-1942 (Box 14, Reel 5772)
        - Ayers, Louis (Trustee; Committee on Nominations), 1930-1943 (Box 14, Reel 5772)
        - BA - BON (Box 14, Reel 5772)
        - Boring, William A. (Treasurer), 1921-1937 (Box 14, Reel 5772-5773)
          (includes reports of visits to Rome with detailed discussion of Academy property, continuation of Professor Sanders's appointment, memorial minute)
        - Brewster, Ethel H. (President, Classical Society of The American Academy in Rome), 1941 (Box 14, Reel 5773)
          (correspondence concerning financial support of the School of Classical Studies by contributing colleges and universities)
        - Brown, Donald F. (Fellow), 1939-1940 (Box 14, Reel 5773)
        - BROWN, F. - BU (Box 14, Reel 5773)
        - Carlton, Newcomb (Trustee), 1931-1938 (Box 14, Reel 5773)
          (correspondence regarding his resignation from the board of trustees)
        - Carpenter, Rhys (Annual Professor; Professor in Charge of Classical Studies), 1926-1940 (Box 14, Reel 5773)
          (letters of appointment, concern about his situation in the event of war, and difficulties in obtaining a passport for Mrs. Carpenter)